<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
    which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
    There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
    An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
    please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
    (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
    (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-larose-capport-architecture-00" ipr="trust200902">
 <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
   <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
        full title is longer than 39 characters -->

   <title abbrev="CAPPORT Architecture">CAPPORT Architecture</title>

   <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

   <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Kyle Larose" initials="K." surname="Larose">
      <organization>Sandvine</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>408 Albert Street</street>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <city>Waterloo</city>
          <region>ON</region>
          <code>N2L 3V3</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 519 880 2400</phone>
        <email>klarose@sandvine.com</email>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="David Dolson" initials="D." surname="Dolson">
      <organization>Sandvine</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>408 Albert Street</street>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <city>Waterloo</city>
          <region>ON</region>
          <code>N2L 3V3</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 519 880 2400</phone>
        <email>ddolson@sandvine.com</email>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>


    <date year="2017" />

   <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
        in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

   <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

   <area>art</area>

   <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

   <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
        IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
        which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

   <keyword>plus</keyword>

   <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
        files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
        output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
        keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

   <abstract>
     <t>This document aims to document concensus on the CAPPORT architecture.
        DHCP, ICMP, and an HTTP API are used to provide the solution.
     </t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
     <t>
       Problems with captive portals have been described in
       <xref target="I-D.nottingham-capport-problem"/>.
     </t>
     <t>
       This document standardizes an architecture for implementing captive portals
       that provides tools for addressing most of those problems.
     </t>
     <t>
       The architecture also attempts to enable IoT devices, in particular
       devices without user interfaces, to navigate a captive portal.
     </t>
     <t>
       The architecture uses the following mechanisms:
       <list style="symbols">
         <t>DHCP/DHCP6 providing end-user devices with a URI in the
            Captive-Portal Router Advertisement option <xref target="RFC7710"/>.
            This URI is an API that the end-user devices access for
            information about what is required to escape captivity.
         </t>
         <t>Notifying end-user devices of captivity with ICMP/ICMP6 "unreachable" messages.
            This notification can work with any internet protocol, not just
            clear-text HTTP. This notification does not carry the portal URI,
            rather triggers the DHCP-provisioned portal to be accessed.
            This notification carries a "reason" that allows the devices
            to receive customized work-flows at the portal.
         </t>
         <t>
            Receipt of the ICMP/ICMP6 messages inform an end-user device
            that it is captive. This permits the device to take immediate
            action to satisfy the portal (according to its configuration/policy).
            The architecture recommends the device to query the
            DHCP-provisioned CAPPORT URI with the specified "reason".
            This API returns a status and a menu for navigating the captive portal.
            Typically one of the menu items is a web page suitable for browsing.
         </t>
       </list>
     </t>
     <t>
       The architecture attempts to provide privacy, authentication, and safety mechanisms
       to the extent possible.
     </t>
     <section title="Requirements Language">
<!-- TODO: remove this section? -->
       <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
       "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
       document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
       target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
     </section>
     <section title="Terminlogogy">
       <t>Captive Network: A network for which communication outside of it is subject to a captive portal</t>
       <t>Captive Portal Enforcement: The device which enforces the captive portal in the captive netowrk</t>
       <t>Captive Portal Client: Also know as Client. A device which wants to communicate outside the captive network</t>
     </section>

   </section>

   <section title="Components">

     <section anchor="section_dhcp" title="DHCP">
       <t>
         A standard for providing a portal URI is described in <xref target="RFC7710"/>.
         The CAPPORT architecture expects this URI to access the API described
         in <xref target="section_api"/>.
       </t>
       <t>
         Although it is not clear from RFC7710  what protocol should be executed
         at the specified URI, it may have been assumed to be an HTML page,
         and hence there may be User Equipment assuming a browser should open this URI.
         For backwards compatibility, it might be necessary for the server
         to check Agent-Id when serving the URI.
       </t>
     </section>
     <section anchor="section_icmp" title="ICMP/ICMP6">
       <t>
         A mechanism to trigger captive portal work-flows in the User Equipment
         is proposed earlier in <xref target="I-D.wkumari-capport-icmp-unreach"/>.
       </t>
       <t>
         The Captive Portal Enforcement function is required to send such
         ICMP messages when disallowed User Equipment attempts to send
         to the network.
       </t>
       <t>
         The ICMP messages MUST NOT be sent to the internet devices. The indications
         are only sent to the User Equipment.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section anchor="section_api" title="Captive Portal API">
       <t>
         The client performs GET at the DHCP-specified URI.
         The response is a JSON document. The following information
         should be available in the response document, allowing
         clients to choose the next step:
         <list style="symbols">
          <t>Quota information (remaining time/bytes/etc.)</t>
          <t>Whether the device is allowed through captive portal or blocked.</t>
          <t>Method of providing credentials to gain access.</t>
          <t>Describe the required credentials to gain access.</t>
          <t>URL of a web page for devices with browsers and humans.</t>
         </list>
       </t>
        <t>
          The API is intended to provide information and a menu of choices
          to support options for interactive or non-interactive clients.
        </t>
        <t>
          The API should support TLS for privacy.
          [Does this API need to be secure, or do we place security at the
          interfaces it points to?]
        </t>
     </section>
     <section anchor="section_client" title="User Equipment">
      <t>
       The User Equipment is the device that a user desires to communicate 
       with a network. The User Equipment communication is typically
       restricted by the Captive Portal Enforcement until site-specific
       requirements have been met.
      </t>
      <t>
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>May be interactive or non-iteractive</t>
        <t>May have different mechanisms for notifying the user of the captive portal</t>
        <t>Needs to recognize the ICMP unreachable message, and to invoke its captive portal
          handling in response to it.</t>
        <t>Needs to cache the URI for the captive portal API from the DHCP lease.</t>
        <t>May cache credentials to automatically respond to captive portal notifications</t>
        <t>Interactive clients typically ask their users how to proceed through interacting
          with the captive portal. Interactions may be as simple as accepting a terms of agreement,
          or as complicated as filling out some forms.</t>
        <t>An example interactive client is a smart phone.</t>
        <t>Non interactive clients may be provisioned with credentials
           out of band (e.g., via USB programming) in order to automatically gain access.</t>
        <t>An example non interactive client is an IoT device such as a smart thermostat.</t>
        <t>May need to distinguish between types of clients here.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
     </section>
     <section anchor="section_capport_enforcement" title="Captive Portal Enforcement">
      <t>
        The Captive Portal Enforcement component restricts network access to 
        User Equipment according to site-specific policy. Typically User Equipment
        is denied network access until it has performed some action.
      </t>
      <t>
       The Captive Portal Enforcement component:
       <list style="symbols">
        <t>Allows traffic through for allowed User Equipment.</t>
        <t>Blocks traffic and sends ICMP notifications for disallowed User Equipment.</t>
        <t>Permits disallowed User Equipment to access necessary APIs and web pages to
           fulfill requirements of exiting captivity.</t>
        <t>May modify responses to canary URLs, or perform other methods of notification.</t>
        <t>Updates policy per User Equipment in response to operations from the Captive Portal API.</t>
       </list>
      </t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <section anchor="section_workflow" title="Solution Workflow">
    <t> This section describes the general workflow of solutions adhering to the architecture. </t>
    <t> 
    Initial connection
    <list style="numbers">
      <t>The client joins the captive network by acquiring a DHCP lease</t>
      <t>The client learns the URI for the Captive Portal API from the DHCP response (rfc7710)</t>
      <t>The client attemps a connection outside the captive network</t>
      <t>The captive portal enforcement device drops the connective requests, and replies with an icmp unreach indicating that it is
       behind a captive portal, and that access is denied (I-D.wkumari-capport-icmp-unreach)
        *** Is this drop okay? ***</t>
      <t>The client handles the icmp unreachable message by invoking its captive portal handling infrastructure</t>
      <t>The captive portal handling infrastructure communicates with the Captive Portal API to gain access to outside the captive network</t>
      <t>The Captive Portal API indicates to the captive portal enforcement device that the client is allowed through</t>
      <t>The client's next connection attempt succeeds.</t>
    </list>
    </t>
    <t>
    Connection about to expire
     <list style="numbers">
      <t>The client sends a packet to the outside network.</t>
      <t>The captive portal device detects that the client's access is about to expire (low quota/time/etc)</t>
      <t>The captive portal sends an icmp unreach to the client indicating that it needs to refresh its access.
            *** Will this interrupt communication somehow? ***</t>
      <t>The client device handles this message by invoking its captive portal handling infrsatructure.</t>
      <t>The captive portal handling infrastructure communicates with the Captive Portal API to gain access to outside the captive network</t>
      <t>The Captive Portal API gives more quota to the client by indicating to the captive portal enforcement device the new, extended quota.</t>
      <t>The client continues unaffected.</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
    Connection expired.
     <list style="numbers">
      <t>The client sends a packet to the outside network.</t>
      <t>The captive portal device detects that the client's access has expired.</t>
      <t>The remaining workflow is that same as for the initial connection.</t>
     </list>
    What happens to a long-running flow here? Does it continue afterwards, or does communication need to be reestablished?
    </t>
   </section>
<!--
   <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
     <t>The authors thank ...
        for their review and suggestions.</t>
   </section>
-->

   <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
     <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>

   </section>

   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
     <!--All drafts are required to have a security considerations section.  See RFC3552 -->
     <section title="Authenticated APIs">
       <t>
         The solution described here assumes that when the client needs to
         trusted the API server, server authentication will be utilized.
       </t>
       <t>
         TODO: this document has not specified the authentication mechanism.
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Risk of Nuisance Captive Portal">
       <t>
         It is possible for any user on the internet to send ICMP packets in an attempt
         to cause the receiving equipment to go to the captive portal. This has been
         considered and addressed in the following ways:
         <list>
           <t>The ICMP packet does not carry the URL, making this method safer
              than 307-redirect methods currently in use.
           </t>
           <t>The ICMP packet carries a token that would not be available, even to an
              on-path attacker. Although possible to guess by brute force, the 
              impact is nuisance due to other precautions.
           </t>
           <t>Even when redirected, the client securely authenticates with API servers.
           </t>
         </list>
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="User Options">
       <t>
         The ICMP messaging informs the end-user device it is being held captive.
         There is no requirement that the device do something about this.
         Devices may permit users to disable automatic reaction to captive-portal indications.
         Hence, support is provided for users who wish to manually navigate the captive portal.
       </t>
     </section>
   </section>
 </middle>

 <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

 <back>
   <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

   <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
    1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
    2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
       (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

    Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
    If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
    directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
    with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
    filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

   <references title="Normative References">
     <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
     &RFC2119;
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7710.xml"?>

   </references>
   <references title="Informative References">
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.wkumari-capport-icmp-unreach.xml"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.nottingham-capport-problem.xml"?>
   </references>

<!--
   <section anchor="app-additional" title="Additional Stuff">
     <t>This becomes an Appendix.</t>
   </section>
-->
 </back>
</rfc>
